[Music]
hello welcome everyone
it is
action livestream number 45.2
it's june 8th 2022. welcome carl
and we are having our third discussion
on the 45
so welcome to the active lab everyone
we're a participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference
this is a recorded and an archive live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve our work all
backgrounds and perspectives are welcome
and we'll be following video etiquette
for live streams
head over to activeinference.org to
learn more about the live streams and
other projects that are happening in
actin flab
we're in active stream number 45.2
it's the third discussion of the paper
the free energy principle made simpler
but not too simple
the first author has joined so thank you
very much for that
and we're going to be
discussing the paper and related topics
so if you're watching live
feel free to write questions and
comments in the live chat and we'll try
to address it if it's within the regime
of attention
otherwise we'll just briefly say hello
and then
dive in to any number of places
so just to begin we can say hi and we
can just mention something we're excited
about or something we liked or
remembered or something that we might
want to resolve by the end of the
discussion
so i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california and i think there was one
question that was submitted by brock
that i would very much like to get into
and also understand the uh role of mass
and inertia for some of these
statistical distributions it's blue
hi i'm blue i'm a researcher in new
mexico
and uh i have you know probably 100
million questions
but uh one one that's been bugging a
long time about
internal states and sensory states
and the influence
whether it's reciprocal or not so
okay and carl anything you'd like to
begin with or lead off
um
well i'm carl
and
as the free energy principle on this
particular one and a bit of focus on
curiosity i'm curious to know what
you're curious about so i was just
trying to remember blue's question there
and how i would uh however how i would
provide a clear answer to it
that's what i find fun answering the
questions
let's um start with a question about
curiosity and then blue you can ask the
question you had where is curiosity in
these curious particles
they
are um
technically
an expression of curiosity uh is an
expression of the imperative to select
those courses of action or policies
that
yield the greatest information gain
and they are
properties of certain particles not all
particles but certain particles
interestingly
the
kinds of particles that conform or look
as if they are
behaving in a way to maximize their
information gain or minimize their
uncertainty about
states that are external to their
markov blanket are those that show very
precise dynamics um
usually associated with
larger particles things like you and me
so
if you work through
the physics and the
dynamics
that particles
who preserve their markov blanket
have and make the further
assumption that you're looking at a
large
classical light particle that conforms
to classical mechanics
then you can demonstrate that the
um active states the way that it acts
upon the environment
um are the product of
beliefs about action
that where that render
the most likely actions those that
maximize information gain
so that's as that's
um a technical answer um for me
mathematically it's all fairly
straightforward but i imagine it might
be a bit mysterious for
if you don't know the underlying mouths
okay great start so blue to your
question
so
this is something that i've read many
times before but but
since i have the opportunity to
interrogate you about it now i i think
it's a good chance
so
here it says
particular partitions can be defined in
terms of sparse coupling perhaps the
simplest definition that guarantees a
markov blanket is as follows
external states only influence sensory
states and internal states only
influence active states
and i find this troubling and i found a
troubling
often in the past because i feel like
internal states can influence
sensory states
like especially in the circumstance
where someone takes lsd your sensory
states are totally then influenced by
your internal
like state of what's going on um
like is it like poking holes in the
markov blanket or
what is happening when uh
the internal states i feel have a great
ability to influence the senses
right i like the notion of poking holes
in your mark off blanket that's
something you wouldn't really want to do
too much if you were that markov blanket
um because that would
basically destroy the the markov blanket
um
and interestingly uh much of uh you know
i i conceive of much of neuroscience is
trying to sort of peer through the mark
of blanket and sometimes you do poke
holes in markov blankets for example in
invasive electrophysiology for example
you know actually so get inside and look
at the internal states but it answered
your question uh which is you know i
think quite an astute question um
those kinds of effects would be mediated
technically about what we call active
states
so it is certainly possible that you can
um
alter the gain or the sensitivity of
your sensory states and your effect your
receptor organs
but that effect is mediated by an active
state so if you look um again at that
sort of influence diagram little arrows
in it
you will see that there is a vicarious
path
in which the internal states can have an
effect and sometimes a profound effect
on the responsiveness or the sensory
states per se but usually what that
translates into is the sensitivity of
the responsiveness of sensory states to
external states so um in the
instance of psychedelics for example um
you you might construe that as um
if the drug was acting
at the level of the retina for example
that might be um
activating
certain active states that are
mediating um attention attention-like
phenomena at a very very low level
probably not the best explanation with
psychedelics i you know i i would
contend that
as anything that affects your perception
is really
something that can be
understood as
a different kind of
belief updating or perceptual synthesis
given the same sensory information so
i'll come back to you and ask you know
well what did you mean by um i know that
my internal states can affect my sensory
states
and you might
do you really mean your sensory states
do you actually mean the rate at which
your
photo receptors or your um
any of your sensory receptors are
actually firing or did you really mean
the sense making that ensues from the
same sensory input due to some internal
um
we sometimes call it internal action but
your some internal
dynamics that
change the belief updating and change
the kind of thing explanation you bring
to the table for this particular pattern
of sensory input
yes and
so i think it's i think it's a little
bit of both i think uh
especially like i like i think of some
um i i i feel like it's maybe uh mdma
that affects like the um the way that
your eyes move in in your head like it
literally affects like your your um
the eyes stockades
so
i i would think that like i guess that's
involuntary action so i guess then it
does
impact the action even though the action
is involuntary
i guess that makes sense so well yes
i just endorse that that makes perfect
sense yeah i noticed what you've done is
you you you're talking exclusively about
action your health reaching the world um
and that obviously underwrites the
sense-making um but of course that's not
internal states affecting the sensory
input it's affecting the way that we
palpate the world and the sensory input
that we get and in a sense that that's
the you know one way in which we express
our curious behavior that we actually
palpate uh volitionally or sub
personally the world with our eyes with
our with us you know sense receptors in
our skin uh and even our intraceptive um
receptors that you know mediate those
gut feelings the these can all be
deployed in particular ways but these
are a reflections of acting on um
acting on the world
in order to produce different kinds of
sensations so that you know
that answer i think um sort of
highlights exactly that sparse coupling
that um underwrites the statistical
separation of internal from external
states
give me another example i think them
the ones that are sort of
counter-intuitive or sort of violations
the most useful to drill down on uh you
know
so like i think of extreme circumstances
also not just like psychedelics but but
you know when you're absolutely parched
uh
like so when you're absolutely punched
you're absolutely famished
so
um
the food smells so much better
when you're absolutely
starving so so that that's another
example of how like my internal states
you know i feel like affect your sensory
perception
that's a great example as well
so i would read that example um
um yeah it makes a number of excellent
points that certainly the the
the the salience of certain sensory cues
in different um
states of being that you you yourself
infer
will be
very context dependent so
you're a nice example the smooth your
the food smells nice when you're hungry
but to if you like articulate that and
to realize that
and also
make plans in terms of what you're going
to do about being hungry you or you have
to have an internal representation not
just of
niceness
but also being hungry you know to
recognize that you are hungry
so i think that example
almost paradoxically speaks to extremely
high level internal states trying to
make sense of all of these interceptive
um cues that are coming in
so that's a nice example um
of interceptive inference so in the same
way we try to make sense of the patterns
of visual input in terms of what caused
that what's the best explanation for
this particular pattern is it a face is
it a bird
at very low levels is it an edge
all those rules in principle should also
apply to
the patent inputs you get from your
autonomic nervous system your
sympathetic and parasympathetic nervous
system and all the receptors
that i repeat literally report your cup
feelings and you have to make sense of
that and some your creatures like you
and me
um
can make sense of it by bringing these
very high level hypotheses like i am in
a state of hunger or i am hungry but
this is just another percept you know
and it's as you know um
has the same status as the percept of a
face you know a face is a sufficient
explanation for what i'm currently
seeing and enables me to make all sorts
of predictions about what's going to
happen uh in terms of you know looking
at that face and hearing the sounds
emanating from that face
knowing that i am hungry also has
enormous benefit in the sense that it
now constrains or provides or conditions
certain prior beliefs about what i'm
likely to do next
including these mental actions that
enable me to attend to certain cues as
opposed to other cues and i think it's
really the smelling nice um
part and parcel of that is that you are
actually attending to olfactory input
but in order to do that you've got to
recognize that the most likely thing i
am likely to do as a hungry creature who
knows that she's hungry is attend to my
old factory input so the mechanism of
attention
interestingly gets into this
into your example as well
um and that's yeah yeah i think that's a
nice observation
in the sense that many people
think that the um
that attention
is a kind of mental action it's an
internal action it's sort of basically
um appealing to this notion of markov
blankets within markov blankets within
the brain and certain high levels acting
upon
lower levels just to set the gain you
know if you're telling a predictive
coding stories will be the precision of
certain um
signals in a folk psychology um rhetoric
this would be the salience of your of uh
of particular um
certain modalities of input that are
whole precise information for you at
that point in time that resolve
uncertainty about the state that you're
in hungry happy
uh fearful you know whatever you know
all of these things have to be inferred
and recognized by the blue updating and
the um the dynamics of the internal
states
okay
um first welcome thomas
uh greetings
talk a little bit about action and how
action integrates these complex nested
chains of of causal narratives so we
talked about different perturbations
whether it's a pharmacological
intervention or some optogenetic or
something like that
there could be a modification at the
level of the retina
and that's directly modifying the sense
states so there we don't need to appeal
to any internal states changing to
change perceptions like you're seeing
something different when there's
different light on the retina
then
as was mentioned there might be
modification of active states of
oculomotor behavior and then carl you
just brought it to the idea of attention
as a mental action
and so looking back at the the
partitioning in this figure
the particular states
are the internal states mu and the
blanket so that's the whole particle as
it moves around that's the entity as
distinguished from
the environment
but there's special attention paid to
the autonomous states which are the
active states and the internal states
and it's almost like these are the ones
where control can be applied either in
this terms of direct ocular motor action
or
the possibility of attention as mental
action and so sense cannot be directly
controlled but
in this strange loop way
it is what uncertainty is being reduced
about which is the outcomes of the
observations
and so distinguishing these different
subsets of the partitions
like the particular states being the
entity the particle and then the
autonomous states being the ones that
have special control degrees of freedom
and the blanket states being the ones
that intermediate or make the internal
and external states conditionally
independent each of these subsets
and maybe even other
subsets
have um special roles in understanding
different
cognitive
informal phenomena like curiosity or
drive and motivation and so on
um and then also the example with the
food i am hungry and then i thought
about what if someone had to believe i
am fasting
and that food smells good but it would
not be pleasant if my fast were ruined
by this sensory outcome
so there's even degrees of cognitive
action
beyond
impulsively following
drives that are of one sensory mode
um
thomas would you like to say hi or
remark on anything you're seeing here or
anywhere else
or there's some questions in the chat
um
so as with last time i apologize a bit
late joining
ran over a little bit at the hospital
so lots of things on the slide that
certainly i'm interested in thinking
about the roles of attention and
and you mentioned the word salience as
well
um and i guess the thing i might pick up
on it is that
um
in relation to the the idea that
attention can be a form of action
and is that we can think about
we can think about the things that are
salient as being things that are worthy
of attending to worthy of um performing
that action that then obtains those
sorts of data
which
i find quite a useful way of
thinking about the relationship between
those two terms and a way of
understanding what we mean when we talk
about
um savings or attention and there's
those sorts of things
um and for me this is one of the
big motivations for
[Music]
using computational neuroscience methods
for using mathematical modeling as a way
of trying to describe what's going on in
that a lot of these terms are used
interchangeably and with very different
meanings by different authors in a lot
of the cognitive sciences and it's quite
useful to be able to pin that down to
something mathematical and unambiguous
that says what i'm talking about is this
you may use the second word for
something something different but at
least we can be clear on what is meant
by it here
and so for me it's one of the things
that i found got me interested in active
inference in the first place this idea
of being able to formalize things in
psychology in
a very precise
way that makes me think of
pinning insects and sometimes by just
pinning a few parts of them
the whole pose might be
stabilized
and then other times you might pin this
bug
and somebody else says well i have this
one that's floating around
it could be pinned down
or
just trying to walk this path between
being clear about how the terms are used
but not partitioning ourself off and
saying well we're ignoring
the casual use of the english word
surprise
or
belief or curiosity or attention or
salience and we're just going to call
that string
onto this other formalism so how to
navigate the way that sometimes the
formalisms do have
uh
words
that tag them
like risk or ambiguity and how to be
clear about something yet when the term
itself may not have sharp distinctions
maybe a lot is cut out or is not um
fully encompassed by that
definition and has issues with then
people taking an unrelated issue or
definition of that word
and projecting that back onto the
formalism
yes and as you say i think it aids with
translation to quite a large degree as
well and
and it's not just shutting yourself off
with one specific
definition that's different to everybody
else's it's a way of saying how can we
how can we actually relate all these
things together and see if there are
multiple different terms that are used
that apply to the same underlying
construct
blue would you like to ask anything or i
can go to a question in the chat
go ahead let's go to the chat
okay i'm gonna ask one shorter question
while preparing another longer one so
ali asks
how can seemingly irrational
non-optimal behavior
in some organisms be accounted for in
active inference different types of
non-optimal or seemingly irrational
behavior whether altruism or making
mistakes
how can these behaviors be understood
within a behavioral optimality framework
did you have any thoughts on that one
first
um
thinking about
balls rolling to the bottom of bowls
one could say
i don't like where this ball rolled
or
i wish things had been different so it
wouldn't have rolled that way
but given where the ball starts
and the structure of the landscape
it's just playing out a certain way
so if somebody has
a very strong aversion to risk
maybe even with the total accurate
information they could still make a
decision where the outcomes are
post hoc perceived as sub-optimal due to
an extreme attention being paid to the
possibility of a downside a one percent
chance you lose one dollar but there's a
99 chance that you get a hundred dollars
but if you're paying a lot of attention
to that one percent chance of loss maybe
that causes somebody to not engage in
this offer that in the mean field or in
this sort of
other way or other set of priors other
attention would be quite relevant so
um
given how things are set up they play
out a certain way and we don't need to
take that too much onto the determinism
path but given a set of priors bayes
optimal or variational bayes utilizing
organisms or those we model as such may
get to outcomes that don't always result
in them achieving their even specified
goals
blue
i think about it in terms of uh the old
expression if you want to go
fast go alone and if you want to go far
go together
it's it's cooperation
and and really in the
effort of achieving any goal
um i think that the
altruistic behavior in terms of of
cooperation well it's
not always
really seen that way i think overall
um
it it is that way so so i mean while
giving ten dollars to a homeless person
in your community might be you know
depriving you of ten dollars
it's also
giving that person the opportunity to
you know have a meal or whatever
um
it just is it's in our nature to be
cooperative whether it's gonna directly
benefit us
or not because it's only through things
like cooperation that we can build
rocket ships and
you know be sitting here today
discussing this paper so we wouldn't
have affordances like the internet if we
didn't um instinctively cooperate
regardless whether it directly benefits
us or not
great point about the scale mattering
you zoom in why is that liver cell
giving up all the glucose isn't glucose
[Music]
something important or pragmatic value
for that cell and it can be true and it
can be playing a service at a higher
level so
thomas or carl
i was just going to pick up on on your
analogy or your metaphor with the bulls
rolling
into the different balls
and
i thought that was quite a nice way of
putting it in the sense that
the optimum trajectory of a ball rolling
into a bowl
um
for any given bowl
is effectively going to be the most
likely path it takes
now of course
you could
you could swap that bowl for a bowl of a
completely different shape
um and you would get a completely
different trajectory so what might seem
optimal as a trajectory for one bowl
might seem completely sub-optimal for
another
and
there's a question that comes up here a
lot in terms of thinking about
psychopathology or disease processes
where people say well how is it that you
can describe that as as engaging in
optimal behavior because clearly what's
happening is so far from the optimum
and suppose the answer is that
you're
referencing optimality with reference to
the wrong bull
and you need to think about what what is
the objective function whenever we're
talking about optimality we need to say
what what is it we're measuring
optimality in relation to
in active influence clearly the
objective function is always going to be
a free energy function
but the specific priors that go into
making up that free energy function will
have a big impact on the shape of the
free energy landscape and therefore
where we're going to end up moving the
kind of trajectories we're going to have
and
so it turns around the question of
saying is something optimal it says
given that it is optional
what is the appropriate objective
function defined in terms of the
appropriate price
thank you carl
yes just to um reinforce all of those
answers um
and provide a succinct way of responding
to this um important question what is
the relationship between active
inference and bounded or
um optimal uh behavior
so one way to um
answer that question
is just to
query the nature of
optimal behavior and bounded rationality
as it's usually defined in behavioral
economics and sometimes in sort of
behavioral psychology um
and
one theorem which brings those kinds of
formulation into question is called the
complete plus theorem
and what that says is that for any pair
of loss functions and behaviors
there exists a set of priors that render
that behavior bayes optimal
so to translate that into the current
conversation what that means is active
inference can describe
any behavior
in terms of bayes optimality um
given
any loss functions
uh if you allow for different priors so
what that tells you is it's it the the
notion of
sub-optimality um is itself a little bit
suspect all you're saying is that there
are um unique prizes that explain this
behavior
and what you normally end up realizing
is that bayes optimality in the general
sense of active inference
is not a way of prescribing optimal
behavior it's a way of describing it
and that description
requires an identification specification
of the prize in the generative model
which is effectively what thomas has
just said
and indeed practical applications of
active inference
to
say in the context of computational
psychiatry are just that they are just
using active inference
in order to summarize or to understand
or characterize a particular person
in terms of the prime beliefs they are
bringing to the table
given um
their
behavior and given their their sensory
states and you're usually using some
kind of economic scheme so i think the
key thing here is that
the principles um that underwrite active
inference are there to describe not to
prescribe just in the same sense that
hamilton's principles principle of least
action
will describe how a
ball travels through the air or a
massive body or the or the um the ball
in the um in the bowl that you were just
discussing and it does not
prescribe optimal behavior until you
specify the shape of the bowl
the particular prize at hand which will
be
or you're by definition different for
every particle every creature and every
person so there is no optimality in the
sense that there is a right way to
behave it's always conditioned on the
prior beliefs of the of the person that
you're talking to
there's a further twist here which
moves on from expected utility theory
and i'd also suggest bounded rationality
which is the the
um the objective function that
underwrites choice behavior
and planning
has two aspects to it it's got the
expected information gain and the
expected cost or the negative expected
utility
but the expected information gain
depends upon what you currently believe
which means that the optimal way to
behave
depends upon what you believe in this
moment so there is no if you like
invariant optimal response because it's
always conditioned upon what you know at
the moment so there may be times when
you um behave in a way that seems to
ignore your prior preferences
in order to resolve some uncertainty and
there'll be other times when that will
be less the uncertainty be less if you
like um potent in determining what the
best next thing or the most likely thing
you're going to do
next
so
i
i i think active inference gracefully
subsumes
um
bounded and optimal behavior
but as special cases when you can ignore
the way that we handle uncertainty
awesome and it makes me think of even in
the fully observable chessboard
situation
there still might not be a single best
move
and so situations with less
observability and more openness in their
affordances it's even more that case so
it's great how you mentioned carl about
the description
rather than the proscription and that um
is followed nicely by a question from
chat so ia roland rodriguez asked
fristen has said the free energy
principle describes particular existence
maxwell ramstead says storms do not
follow fep while water does
i deduce then
that for fep the stone exists but the
storm does not
is that accurate or otherwise can
anything be said to exist that is not
able to be described by the fep
so
if fep is about describing rather than
proscribing
what can be described with the fvp
that's a difficult question
i'm tempted to get thomas to answer that
well i i'll give him a starter while
he's gathering his thoughts um
so yeah fristen has says fep i think
probably ramstead uh talks about did he
talk about storms or stones um because
interestingly storms
are somewhat difficult to describe
because defining the markov blanket of a
storm um is not quite so easy as
defining a markov blanket of a stone
so i'm going to assume that we're
talking about stones as opposed to
storms um
and so the answer would be
the fep
applies to
anything
where a thing is defined stipulatively
in terms of possessing a markov blanket
that enables you to distinguish the
states that belong to the thing
from
any other states so if something exists
then the fep applies does um so that's
that's one thing that can be said very
very clearly
um the next question is well are there
different kinds of things um and the
answer would be yes absolutely and and
it depends very much upon the causal
diagrams we're looking at the influence
diagrams that we were looking at before
in terms of the sparsity of what
influences what
so
stones
may be construed as
as markov blankets um
that
don't have any overt active states so
they could be construed as inert things
that where inert things could be
described as um markov blankets or
possessing a particular partition which
is another way of saying it possesses a
markov blanket and
yeah you can distinguish it from a stone
from um familiar in which the stone is
found but that particular kind of
particle um or markov blanket
is inert in the sense it doesn't move
around very much
if that doesn't move around at all
in an autonomous way so that immediately
distinguishes between
two kinds of particles within without
active states um you can go on sort of
um
defining different spaces structures and
different kinds of things and
until we get back to the um
and daniel you mentioned strange loops
before um and there there is certainly
an interesting strange loop that emerges
when when one's active states or one's
actions are hidden from the internal
states and what does that mean well it
means that now my active states become
causes of my sensations but i don't know
that
therefore now because i am i can read my
internal dynamics
as
belief updating about my the causes of
my sensations i now
um can be read as
forming beliefs
about the causes of sensations that
include my own actions and at this point
you have a mathematical image of
planning
that you move from things like
thermostats um and viruses through to um
people um and you know anything that has
a sufficiently
deep or expressive genitive model
to cover its own action so now you get
into the world
uh kinds of things that look as if they
engage in
in planning and sometimes that's framed
in terms of planning as inference and
that would be um that would be
an apt way to describe you know a lot of
the you know a lot a lot of the
biological self-organization we are
interested but not all of it uh you are
you could content the virus doesn't plan
uh you could even contend that
at a different scale evolution doesn't
plan it's not everything
plans but there will be certain kinds of
things mark off blankets particular
petitions that look as if they do plan
thomas your turn
i don't know quite what i'm supposed to
add to that um
[Music]
i i suppose
an alternative perspective on the
question or well more accurately an
alternative question is which systems is
it useful to try and describe with the
pre-energy principles
and i think
what carl's described in terms of some
of the special cases the things that
you know
is it useful to describe the stone in
terms of the free energy principle
almost certainly not
um
you sort of add in the additional
additional baggage and things but it's
not really doing any inference of an
interesting sort
um
and
perhaps the best way of answering that
question is to look at the sorts of
things the free energy principle has
been applied to
and that have found some sort of
purchase
clearly looking at um including looking
at the cognitive neurosciences that's
and where it's had a particular impact
and i would imagine that part of the
reason for that is that what's so
interesting about um brains and behavior
is that what goes on inside a brain is
uh is
um
almost by definition it is only
interesting because it's
something that relates to what's going
on outside of that brain
so
the whole business of doing neuroscience
is about relating internal and external
states and the the way in which the clue
relate to one another
and so it's only once you
once you start looking at systems like
that that you you really need to appeal
to this kind of formalism
great
um so just a few uh notes on this
um
carl you mentioned different kinds of
things
and um
what
taxonomies or classification schemes of
things exist along what dimensions do
things exist
and how does
the fep
bring cohesion
or highlight tensions in the ways that
kinds of things have been identified
um like
mental versus
physical constructs or just a few that
were were mentioned
um different extent of
seemingly internal cognitive states
then you mentioned
the difference of the extent of the
autonomous action
and then i think what the question and
it was clarified a bit in the chat about
the storm and the stone was about
resistance to dissipation resistance um
in its persistence
so
where do
dissipative
persistent
regenerative
propagative
cascading failing systems
growing
systems
what what how do we think of those
as different types of things
well technically
it all boils down to the functional form
of the dynamics um
so
um
from from the point of view the free
energy principle i should say that you
know
this is a very colloquial view which is
just emerging you know over the past few
years and indeed over the past few weeks
so you know this is not accepted wisdom
nor is there any consensus about it but
if you want to
an answer from first principles um
then you you start where the free energy
principle starts which is in the
dynamics and the the dynamics are
defined by
a stochastic differential equation or
sometimes known as a random dynamical
system um in physics this is just the uh
the longevity equation
um and so any different kind of system
and implicitly um if there is a thing in
the system then there has to be a
particular partition that you know that
that's something which is at the heart
of the free energy principle it's it's
defining thing that's in terms of the
ability to separate states of the thing
from other states so
by definition we're talking about markov
blankets
and as soon as you write down a
particular partition that implies or
requires a markov blanket
then
you you have the opportunity now to look
at the functional form
of the influences of different states
and other states and then you can now if
you like knock out
further causal influences to create a
taxonomy of increasing capacity
of systems and ask questions what sorts
of behaviors would these
more and more sparse um
systems
demonstrate and one nice example that
we've just been discussing
is if we cut the connection
in the functional form of the coupling
amongst the subsets of the particular
partition between the active states and
the internal states
so that now the
active states my action
now becomes hidden
from the internal states because it's
been uncoupled then it becomes a hidden
cause of my sensations and i get a very
different kind of
interpretation of the
internal thoughts in terms of belief
updating so that's one nice example of
what would emerge just by thinking about
um things
in terms of their dynamical architecture
namely the functional form of the
dynamical coupling between different
different um different subsets of things
you also introduced a very important
another distinction
so that would be if you like one
dimension
[Music]
along which you would be able to
elaborate different kinds of things
different classes of things different
categories of things of increasing
sparsity and probably in the increase in
the sparsity increasing sophistication
and you're more closer to things like us
basically you know the sparse you get um
the the closer you will get to you know
to to um and you know things that show
autonomous behavior of of an intentional
kind that has this planning aspect but
there's another crucial distinction
which you uh
which is the distinction between
um particular states that are
dissipative
versus um conservative now in this
instance
for all things that exist for a given
period of time
then the markov blanket has to be there
because that definitionally
specifies the existence of the thing so
that's an existential imperative but
within that
non-dissipating markov blanket you can
have
particular states namely autonomous
internal active plus sensory states
that belong to big things and that's
important because with big things
all the random fluctuations that do the
thermodynamic dissipation are averaged
away and they start to behave like
classical objects so you have this
distinction between small things
whose internal states and sensory states
and active states could show lots of
random fluctuations you know possibly
even down to the quantum level
versus big things like you and me
that actually obey um
almost
lacrosse mechanics classical mechanics
newton's laws of motion for example or
electrodynamics in terms of the you know
behavior of neural populations and the
like
so these classical dynamics are subject
to exactly the same
rules and principles that underwrite the
free energy principle
but in this special case
all of the internal active and sensory
paths
dynamics are paths of least action
because you've averaged away because
you've coarse grained to an extent that
there are no more random fluctuations
and that creates a very different kind
of behavior um
that you know
again moves us um into the realm of
creatures that plan basically um simply
because they have this precise kind of
damage so
in summary from the point of view of
just the maths i think the taxonomy
you're looking for which i don't think
is actually out there yet but could be
in in the fullness of time and i just
said the reason i don't think it's quite
out there
is if you look at physics
um up until now
no one's really got beyond just saying
there exists a heat bath or a scrutiny
potential or a heat reservoir um so they
haven't really thought about um a part
you know the
partition into a heat bath the thing
that's contained by the heat mouth and
the thing that contains the heat bath
which is the external states so there
isn't really a mechanics that really
talks about thickness in this explicit
uh
way
which is one reason i suspect there
isn't actually at this stage of physics
of different kinds of things but if that
if there is my guess is it would be
articulated in terms of the sparse
coupling amongst partitions of a
particular
subsets of a particular petition
and um whether or not
certain subsets are or their dynamics
are subject to um
non-trivial random fluctuations and
uncertainty
awesome
well fairly we all expect and prefer
such a taxonomy so people can probably
guess how that will influence our future
policy selection
it also takes us to a question that
brock had raised uh in the week between
the dot one of the dot two
so brock asked i'm interested in how
markov blankets interact and affect one
another specifically when their scales
differ by many orders of magnitude
for example baseball versus the air
molecules dna in a cell nucleus versus
the environment alpha particles versus
dna
it sometimes seems the larger scale
overwhelms the smaller scale and vice
versa conditioned on some particular
time skip
i'm wondering if we're considering the
markov blanket as its markov chain into
the past and future if that relative
scale is taken into account
some things have shorter or longer
markov chains that could possibly
explain the seeming flip-flopping of
direction of effects in their relative
mass scales
or is there some generalized synthesis
of action
free energy
that considers both of these and others
to explain the direction of effects
so how do dynamically
potentially dynamically changing
boundaries
and multi-scale systems come together to
help us understand
cascading
top-down or bottom-up effects
well done you should answer that from
the point of view of evolution
okay here would be one thought and and a
a precursor non-fep perspective on this
is synergetics
the uh version of hermann haykin 1983
classic citation multiscale systems like
the ripple and the wave
where is it that changing the ripple
influences the wave and vice versa
as well as synergetics which is a more
geometric perspective that bucky fuller
provides so people have been thinking
about what kinds of top-down and
bottom-up effects
are
causing cascading changes in multi-scale
systems
and then to bring it to evolution like
you suggested
the
structure of the system so the system as
received by the current moment
sets up certain affordances
for very similar stimuli to
propagate through a system in a
non-linear way so for example like
a pheromone of a given shape
might
bind to a receptor with high affinity
that opens local channels that makes
that neuron fire and that amplifies and
so that causes a change at the
organismal behavior level
because of the shape of that
perturbation but then just adding one
methyl group or modifying the chemical
very slightly
so a very similar stimuli or a photon of
a wavelength outside of the receptive
range of a given visual receptor doesn't
induce that kind of a cascading change
so
perhaps it could just be said that the
the structure of the system and maybe
even the sparsity
of the connection amongst subunits
predisposes it in a given moment
to have what appears to be
almost exquisite sensitivity for certain
kinds of changes
while very similar changes next door
may have very little effect
and that potentially at a higher level
evolution
through the inter intra and
inter-generational time scales
gets to a multi-level
position
where
the kinds of
stimuli that one wouldn't want to have
propagate through the system don't
and the kinds of stimuli that one would
want to have propagate through the
system do
because that multiscale system is the
most responsive and adaptive over
multiple time scales
otherwise there might be something
highly
sensitive at one scale but it's at a
blind alley at another time scale or
vice versa
yes to blue
i instantly thought of evolution as soon
as i heard that question um
and really uh thinking about um where a
situation where
the particle of larger mass
uh is overwhelmed by a particle of
smaller mass i thought about this the
sperm cell so like upon fertilization i
think that the particle of smaller mass
completely overwhelms the particle of of
larger mass although
the blanket of the the sperm cell i
think is then subsumed into the
the mother of the of a baby um but but i
was reminded of the paper by matt sims
that we discussed about counting
biological minds
and the interaction between vibrio
fisheries and the squid
when the the i mean the squid go in and
out or the the vibrio fisher i go in and
out of the squid in a very like um
pretty it seems like very magical daily
cycle and um
compose the light organ or cause the
squid to like light up and enable its
hunting
behavior or facilitate its hunting
behavior because then it doesn't cast a
shadow over the organisms that it's
hunting
and in this situation it's interesting
it's these non-linear effects
it's not one
uh little bacteria that can make a squid
light up but it's got to be like a
sufficient concentration of bacteria
that that cause the lighting up of of
the squid
and it's like a a compounded effect so
um here like the the small markov
blankets of each individual bacterial
particle uh uh
really um
maybe overwhelm the larger system and i
i don't know i i feel that way also
about humans the microbiome and the work
that we've um you know learned over the
last
20 years 10 years maybe
about the microbiome and its importance
in human behavior uh the gut brain
access just overall
human function functionality
and toxicity and so forth so so i think
that that all these small markov
blankets really that have have
a very important effect
and non-linear but it does seem to take
a
quite a mass of them to make an impact
can i just come in on the on the
just to
pick up on this um
synchronization of
large ensembles of uh similar kinds of
markov blankets i think it's a very
important notion it does strike me the
sort of three fundamental issues buried
in this question there's this sort of
ensembles of markov blankets
and then there's the
link between different scales so mark
off blankets of markov blankets um and
then how does this manifest in terms of
intuitive concepts like maths
so
just to rehearse what you're what's just
been said
from um
distinguishing between ensembles of
markov blankets at the same scale
then you now have a mathematical image
of um
multicellular organization through to um
eco niche construction through to cult
you know cultural aspects of your
evolutionary psychology in terms of lots
of people interacting together and this
has
many many fascinating aspects
the one
if you like
heuristic that i always keep referring
to when
trying to understand what
a free energy-like principle would
would bring you is that because the
variation free energy is an extensive
property
it means that the
free energy of the ensemble of a
collection of multiple markov blankets
all talking to each other or coupled to
each other via their uh blanket states
um
is the the can be cast as the sum of
each individual uh free energy and if
you just um
simplify the notion of free energy as
predictability what you're saying is
that the
um
the
likely state of an ensemble is that in
which they've jointly minimized their
free energy by making everything
mutually predictable and this normally
um is manifest
as generalized synchronization which is
exactly the sort of you know the
the the behavior of um bugs
that
light up in together or birds that flock
together
so you you see this and you could
actually argue that sort of things like
language
are just one
um expression
of a way
to ensure that we're all mutually
predictable and ensuring that we are
jointly mutually predictable means that
jointly we can minimize our free energy
so there's lots of really interesting uh
sort of directions that you can take
that notion of what would happen if you
put lots of uh markov blankets together
the other the second thing which i think
um you know speaks more to the
evolutionary thing
is the the link between blankets of
blankets at different scales and you
know we
we've just heard in the previous answers
that this normally entails not only a
coarse graining
um moving if you like up in terms of the
spatial scale but absolutely crucially a
temporal scale and i think that that's
absolutely crucial the fact that um
the um
the markov blanket at a lower scale
is likely to less to last for a shorter
amount of time than the markov blanket
at the bigger scale so it's perfectly
permissible to apply the free energy
principle to mark off blankets that
exist for a short period of time from
the point of view of a larger scale
and allow for a metamorphosis of face
transition emerging a mark off blankets
with the other sperm and the egg cell
but from the point of view of the scale
above this is perfectly permissible um
so the free energy principle only
applies at the time scale
that is associated with the level in
question but now the game is to
understand how
the markov blanket of markov blankets at
the scale above
couples to the scope below and vice
versa and this brings us to all sorts of
delicate issues about um
you know how you would read evolution
and epigenetics as
prescribing short-lived markov blankets
in phenotypic time for example
it also again speaks to
this fundamental role of the separation
of time scales that daniel was talking
about in relation to synergistics you
know fast and slow modes um so i think
that that kind of um
thinking about things from different um
different point of view of a separation
of
um temporal or spatial temporal scales
begs some deep questions about top-down
and bottom-up causation that is um
if you like can be articulated in terms
of the endurance of markov blankets at
any particular scale finally the mass
thing is interesting
it relates very much to
the scale
so mass at a quantum level is usually
read as the inverse amplitude of random
fluctuations
um so if you're looking for the sort of
you know the intuitive notion of mass uh
as dictating the behavior of a very
small particle at the quantum scale
then the you know the quantity that
underwrites that is the amplitude of the
um of the random fluctuation so as
things get hotter
with more and more random fluctuations
they tend to have they look as if they
have smaller mass
but as you get bigger and bigger and
bigger and you move into the world of
lagrangian mechanics and classical
mechanics and the random fluctuations
disappear
then you're in the world now where mass
takes on a very different meaning and it
effectively can be regarded as a an
active state in the sense that my mass
attracts you so i act on you through my
mass attracting you
and then you're in the world of general
relativity uh end body problems um and i
mentioned in body problems because they
the only thing that makes them
interesting is exactly the
non-linearities that blue was talking
about uh so you know if you didn't have
those nonlinearities and there's
solenoidal flows that underwrite
lagrangian mechanics um
the orbiting of the heavenly bodies or
anything that oscillates you know in a
classical sense and then then you would
not have
the itinerant dynamics that the
characteristic of non-equilibrium
systems that that conform to classic
classical mechanics
so
just the notion of mass i think is
itself really very interesting and takes
on very very different meanings
mathematically depending upon whether
you're working a very very small scale
or a very large scale
this is kind of a call back to our
previous discussion
we talked about three generalizations
we talked about generalized synchrony
generalized coordinates of motions and
generalized homeostasis
and so i'm actually seeing these
reflected in your response and in your
trilemma carl um the ensembles of markov
blankets at the same scale of similar or
different kinds of things
is a general synchronization and again
that doesn't mean lockstep that means it
could be turn taking as a generalized
mode to
allow for this mutual predictability and
that's generalized synchronization
and then the second point had to do with
the relationship between scales whether
that's accomplished with a
renormalization or with some other
framework from synergetics and that made
me think about the generalized
coordinates in space and time
and kind of like a gps coordinate
not exactly but it's like scales of 10
in space and so there's some coordinate
systems that help us navigate
multi-scale spatial and temporal
with um this
notion that things that are things for
shorter amounts of time tend to be
smaller
and even things that have large spatial
extent and are short-lived
the smaller parts of them are even more
short-lived so it's kind of true within
and between different kinds of things
and then this final one
i feel like should connect to
generalized homeostasis i was thinking
about the orbiting
of the planets
as a generalized homeostasis
in some way like the non-linearity
is such that it isn't just
collisions and repulsions
but actually there is an attracting set
and there's biorhythms
that are
predicated upon the generalized
synchronization
and the generalized coordinates somehow
and that allows for multi-scale
generalized homeostasis which is to say
persistent multi-scale things
let's go to a slightly different and
technical question
this is from
ml don
who wrote
say in our generative model we have n
numbers of possible states s
given observation o we would like to
estimate
p s
conditioned upon o equals o using
variational inference
what if we needed the n plus first state
variable
in order to describe the true posterior
better
similar to thinking out of the box by
adding dimensions
so partially observable states would
mean two things
one i don't know how many states i need
so i need to be flexible in thinking out
of the box for better estimation of p s
conditioned on o
and two given observation o i am not
certain what state i am in
could you please discuss the idea of
flexible growing and pruning of states s
while estimating the true posterior
so this is a question that's come up
occasionally over the last few years
and i i remember ryan smith did some
work on exactly this
question
specifically on how you might grow
the states in your model
um
so
i think it's still an open question as
to what the optimal way of adding in new
states or new hypotheses is
but i think the way of evaluating
whether those additional hypotheses are
useful is is much better established
so beyond the answer to the the second
part how do you evaluate whether it's
useful to have an additional state or
hypothesis as part of your model or not
is
simply to to perform a basin model
comparison so
you calculate the marginal likelihood or
a free energy approximation to that
when the state is in play and then
another one when it's not
um it's interesting to to note that the
question highlights both growing and i
think pruning was in there as well um
and that
it's interesting it's much easier to
prune them away
than it is to work out how to add in new
states
um
and we can do that very efficiently
using methods like bayes and model
reduction
which effectively say let's let's sort
of run the model
uh or fit our model
when we've got all of our hypotheses in
play
and then test
post hoc alternative models
in which we've set the prior probability
of certain states to zero or to nearly
zero to compare how much better would
our model be without it
and it's better in the sense that we
managed to reduce the complexity of the
model we're using we simplify things and
comply with occam's razor while
maintaining a high degree of accuracy in
how we predict the data
which are the accuracy and complexity
terms that we get in a marginal
likelihood or free energy
so
if we had a simple way of adding in
additional states
um then
then it's just simply a matter of then
calculating with that additional state
is the marginal likelihood improved or
not
um
[Music]
an alternative way is to say well no
actually let's just take the pruning
perspective let's just start from a very
large number of states and an over
parameterized generated model of our
world with many hypotheses
that we don't possibly think are ever
going to really be there and then simply
prune them away
in relation to the data we have until
we've got the simplest accurate
explanation for those data
it's very interesting about um after
a proposal is on the table
whether we're in the bayesian
or we're in the frequentist world
evaluating alternatives can be done with
a defined
approach but it is how you get the
proposal onto the table
what generates new alternatives because
the space of model
modifications may be like
pragmatically or even in principle
open-ended especially if we allow for
very complex
structural maneuvers
like nesting of models
that is basically open-ended in which
proposals are possible
however those may be modeled as actions
of some
model builder
and then they have certain affordances i
can add nodes remove nodes connect add a
connection remove a connection or
perform these structural modifications
and then it could be something like a
genetic algorithm or some other policy
selection
approach that results in the space being
heuristically or adaptively explored in
terms of model structures
but it's never going to be as defined of
a question as
comparing
alternatives because that has um a very
specific
kind of
plug and chug basis
unlike the creativity and the
open-endedness associated with making
model changes
yes and the point you make about
finding a way of
a set of operations to build a model is
an interesting one as well and instead
we had some discussions with giovanni
pizzulo as well not not long ago
and thinking about exactly what sort of
operations those might be
whether it be duplicating parts of a
model adding in hierarchical levels or
taking them away adding in states taking
them away
and and
and how that might
manifest in terms of natural selection
of models over and development of
cognitive architectures over
um evolutionary time
cool we did discuss uh at least one
paper of pizzulo at all
that was talking about the simple
homeostatic architecture and how that
could be um
turned into a more anticipatory
structure and so on
um
let's
turn back to
the roadmap
daniel before we go i just mentioned
there's three things which people um
might have heard about which would be uh
sort of use related to what you just
been discussing the first thing is
structure learning in radical
constructivism so the work of people
like josh tenenbaum and how to grow a
mind i think was his title of one of his
popular
papers so this is exactly the same
problem you've been discussing what are
the rules and principles for growing
morals and learning the structure of a
model that could include and you know an
n plus one state so that's a very
interesting literature um the other um
probably more technical um
take on this is called non-parametric
bays
where there are priors
um
um used to decide whether to include or
not state n plus one given you are
currently using just states one to n and
they rest upon things called stick
breaking processes like the chinese
restaurant process
so there is a quite a literature out
there in terms of
structuring the growth of a model
usually i repeat usually under the
rubric of
non-parametric base
and then finally
in economics
there is a
an ideology that rests upon
this distinction between
not knowing
having uncertainty
about states of the world
and having uncertainty about states that
have never been encountered or
represented before and that's sometimes
referred to as radical uncertainty so
which is meant to distinguish just
between just being uncertain about
states of affairs to be
knowing that i just don't even know
these states could ever happen um
so
interestingly radical uncertainty is
usually used as a motivation for not
committing to a
probabilistic or bayesian
description of things so you move into
sort of heuristics of the gerd gigaren's
sword and narrative explanations for
things
but i think if you you know if you
cast radical uncertainty as exactly the
kind of problem that you've been trying
to think about principle solutions for
you can probably bring that kind of um
economic perspective back into um
into formal maths uh just one final
point and this relating to the previous
question uh about um ensembles and the
conclusion that we all try to make our
worlds as predictable as possible that
sort of suggests you don't need to grow
morals very much
if there is a case that we construct our
own universes in a way to make them
predictable then we actually don't need
very complex uh models so i i wonder
whether in fact the shrinking or the
bayesian model reduction
is perfectly fit for purpose and
certainly it's consistent with them with
me in the sense that i was born with too
many neurons and too many connections
and as i get older i just lose stuff but
at least i become more fit for purpose
modeling my little world which you all
carefully keep very predictable for me
and thank
you um i'll connect that
to uh one uh
common casual framework but in a recent
paper with scott david and rj corday we
we connected rumsfeld's quadrant the uh
unknown known known unknown
and interestingly in that famous quote
by rumsfeld if um people look at it
there's he only mentions three of the
quadrants
and the unknown known
is actually like a hidden quadrant
and we sort of in a preliminary way
asked what do these different situations
mean for different knowledge about
particular states so no known includes
the metacognitive aspect of knowing
not only all the partitioned states but
also the policy
and then in the unknown known the
partitions are known but what is unknown
is actually the policy you got the atom
level description of the car but you
still might not know what policy to take
in terms of using the card
and then knowing unknown is basically
the bounded rationality bounded at the
perimeter of the particulate entity
because the internal and blanket states
are known as well as potentially even
what to do
but the external state has high
uncertainty and then this unknown
unknown which is that radical
uncertainty might include like not
knowing what's out there or how to
pursue it and there might be different
mappings too but um that was just
coming to mind with this question about
uncertainty about states of the world
and then uncertainty of states that
haven't been observed before
let's return to the roadmap
on our road trip
and um is there a section
that somebody feels like
plays
well here or section that we haven't
been able to
cover any of the figures or formalisms
of
so i don't think we've covered any of
the
figures except for figure one maybe we
want to look into the
figure two autonomous flow manifold flow
great so yes we did spend um a lot of
time talking about the particular
partition
in this discussion and in many other
discussions and it's really important
it's the
particular physics but it would be
awesome to
just spend a few minutes on each of the
subsequent figures
what is being shown
what do the axes or formalisms represent
and what are the implications of the
figure
so here we have figure two or carl or
thomas what is being shown in figure 2
i suppose there are there are a couple
of things being shown in figure two
um
i think the the graphic on the left
with the spiral is
quite a nice way of demonstrating this
idea of
there being some um solenoidal element
to the flow
which is causing it to
sort of have this circular structure
um
that then
as a consequence of having the
the um
the dissipative part of the flow with
this these gamma terms the difference
between the cubing the solenoid and the
gamma being the um
the dissipative part of this flow and
that that then reduces the amplitude of
this spiral over time and you end up
with this settling to some point
um
so
it's just setting out the the two
different directions really that things
can evolve it
um
and
i'm trying to remember exactly what the
equations were in the paper that led to
the the expression in terms of the um
the alpha and the bold alpha
um can't they remember that better um
is it called was this a least action
path that we were talking about here in
terms of the bold alpha is this the
settling to the least action
yeah yeah and
um
it's
an analysis which people might come
across when they look at things like the
center manifold theorem or indeed the
slaving principle that um
daniel was just talking about from
synergetics you've got these sort of
fast fluctuations that are drawn to a
center manifold in our case the center
manifold or the manifold that sort of
draws trajectories to it are the paths
of least action
that
constitute in the joint space of the
external and
internal autonomous states that
synchronization manifold but in this
instance
not synchronization between people but
synchronization between the inside and
the outside
three and how about the right side
sorry i meant the dark line on the right
hand side
was meant to be the uh the
synchronization manifold to which um
to which your all trajectories are drawn
and
largely lie upon that synchronization
manifold and any perturbations um um
sort of collapse back to or drawn back
to that manifold in the spirit of the
left-hand side of the diagram so um
so using words like manifold is to
emphasize this is very much related to
the center manifold theorem it also
speaks to one way of describing
generalized synchronization of chaos or
generalized synchrony which is collapse2
or constraint constrained flows on a
synchronization manifold
so this is just your one way of
graphically illustrating um
awesome
any other
thoughts on too
where's the uh housekeeping term
the lambda
because there's the q
and the gamma but as we've discussed in
live stream 32
there's another term there too
so i think that the q and the gamma here
are sort of implicitly
being treated as constants so they're
not varying over state space in in this
particular graphic
uh and so the housekeeping term will
only will only appear whether it's some
variation depending upon where you are
in state space
[Music]
in principle you've put it back there
um by allowing those slightly more
complicated
trajectories um with
more interesting solenoidal flows i
think normally we tend to just assume
that the the space is defined such that
the gamma term can be treated as
effectively a diagonal or an even an
identity matrix or at least a block
diagonal type matrix
that gets a little bit more complicated
when working in generalized coordinates
of motion because of the structure that
the blocks have to account for
the correlations between
uh different orders of motion but
but doesn't necessarily have to vary
depending on where you are in space
awesome
you go
you should feel licensed to ignore the
housekeeping term in most
people it gets too complicated
okay on to
three
so three
was labeled as markov blankets and
self-evidencing
what is being shown in three
uh well i'll i'll do this briefly then
then one of you could take over it it
was just um
this slide is usually um
used to
illustrate that um
the the free energy formalism or
understanding dynamics as gradient flows
on a an energy functional
is unremarkable in the sense that it has
a lot of construct validity in relation
to
existing and
legacy formulations
of behavior usually of a normative kind
and by normative i just mean that
there's some objective function that is
being um extremized so it's just meant
to to illustrate that um
the the
this um
physics-like formulation in terms of um
dynamics
and gradient flows on this free energy
functional um looks and is in a position
to formalize lots of existing theories
and constructs such as reinforcement
learning natural control theory provided
you now read um the objective function
as a log preference well
the log of your prior
prior preferred states uh and you know
i'm just showing that taking different
perspectives on um normative accounts of
uh behavior
um
is
very uh they're all formally uh
very very related um in the sense for
example that the negative of value so
defined
becomes self-information
if you're you're sort of if you were not
an economist and you were an information
theorist you would read the same
quantity basically a self-informational
surprise or surprise and you you
wouldn't talk about expert utility
theory you talk about maximum efficiency
and information theoretic sense
if you were somebody like him and haken
and thinking about synergetics you'd be
taking the average of the
self-informational surprise and then
these dynamics would be basically the
thing you are aspiring to understand and
describe from the point of view of
synergetics and if you're a physiologist
uh homeostasis and of course if you're a
statistician or somebody like us um
who's interested in the uh
if you like the pure probability theory
um
then you can interpret
the uh these gradient flows as
articulating um or at least describing
things like the basic brain hypothesis
so it was just an attempt to show that
there is just one simple dynamic under
the hood of all of these well-accepted
well-proven um
accounts of
normative behavior
why is free energy principle
in the blue cell
um i i think just because
it could be described as a a a principle
articulated in terms of information
theory um where information theory is
just a probability theory with some
geometry
okay and while we're on this question of
unification
what does the cover of the active
inference textbook
i'm curious to hear what you think
tradition dictates that blue go first
isn't it like the one ring to bind them
the one ring to find them and the one
ring to rule them all or like that that
um no really i i've given a
really um
it's like the lord of the rings
um reference except like instead of the
inscription
there's math
[Laughter]
uh anyway
there's there's the funny
take
of of the things i see
before we hear um two thirds of the
answer um yes there's the lord of the
rings reference and also it's a a
blanket
and it's a particle and it that's the
equations that are about partitioning
internal from external states
and so the
with a minimal amount of text
and the minimal number of threes
presented mind brain and behavior par
pizzulo and fristen
there is the partition
column in two minds as to whether we we
tell them
i thought it feel like it's more
interesting having these different
interpretations
yeah
okay
i won't push it let's go to figure four
well no just to say that
that's very clever
also you know we didn't realize how
clever um i think this is thomas and
giovanni came up with this uh but um
completing the ring with an extra equal
sign was quite an insight for me at some
point can you remember that thomas was
that was that you or bob who suddenly
spotted the uh the idea of making
everything equal in a
true causality
yeah and
i think it was giovanni had she raised
the equal sign
[Music]
now but now we have three other ways of
selling this very clever uh clever
little icon yes i wish we thought
okay in figure four
it's describing generic and precise
particles
so what are being shown here
um i'll take this one because uh
i did this one um so this is exactly the
um
trying to depict the distinction we were
talking about before when we asked you
about a taxonomy of different kinds of
things and i was just saying
it's useful to make a distinction
between very small quantum scale things
and large classical scale things where
the particles are sufficiently large
that the um the random fluctuations go
away and every
or a particular path
is a path of least action and in this uh
specific case
there are certain um
sources of uncertainty that disappear
that manifest as a collapse of
certain uncertainties and
that can be captured
using what's called an information
diagram so this is an information
diagram and it's basically you can
understand
the areas
as uncertainty or entropy
and the
left hand set of panels is in the
general case that would be suitable for
um
[Music]
very small particles
showing the shared and unique
information
between the
between a partition into external
sensory and um for simplicity autonomous
states here uh and the areas of
intersection can be read as a mutual
information
um
so
what you can see on
on the right hand side the left-hand
side
um
is that there is uncertainty
still in the game
even when i have i know everything else
so there is a unique uncertainty
associated with
um
every one of the states
but if i now move to precise particles
or particles that behave as if they were
more classical in nature
there are um
a lot of uncertainty disappears in the
sense that the only source of random
fluctuations is on the at the paths or
the dynamics of the external states
which means that if i um knew
the um
external and autonomous states then i
would be able to predict precisely the
paths of least action or the paths that
uh a sensory state would take in the
absence of any um random fluctuations so
the unique uncertainty associated with
the sensory states s disappears um
similarly um if i knew the external
states and the sensory states um then
there is no uncertainty about the path
of autonomous states so the unique pink
part associated with alpha the
autonomous states disappears
and that has the interest interesting
implication
that the uncertainty
about the both the sensory and
active uh st
autonomous states has to be the same
if
the um if you knew the external states
um here denoted by eta and and other
things so for example um there is no
uncertainty about active states given
sensory states which means that the
active states on the right hand side
have to lie within the sensory states
and you may be asking well why is this
useful
well it becomes incredibly useful
when you apply those constraints those
um
things like the uncertainty about
both
autonomous and sensory states given
external states have to be the same for
example and that there is no uncertain
the uncertainty about external states
given sensory states
is the same as the uncertainty of uh
external states given both sensory and
autonomous states for example all of
these little sort of if you like
constraints that ensue
from the simple move from big from small
to big particles get into
um
an expression for the probability
distribution over autonomous paths and
it is this these set of constraints
that lead to
a
functional form
for the expected free energy
which can be decomposed into what we
were talking about before which is
expected information gain and the
expected cost in the absence of those
constraints that expected information
game would disappear they would it would
all come it would the things would
cancel out in the general case so this
is if you like a math you know a
visualizable
way of
looking at the information decomposition
among the part of the particular
partition
in the context of
the general case and the in the context
of precise case just to visualize the
constraints that lead to curious
behavior
so if you remember it is expected
information gain
that describes
apparent curious behavior because
actions become more likely if they
increase expected or have a high
expected information gain or resolve
uncertainty or minimize entropy of a
conditional sort
so that this is if you like a a visual
aid memoir or an unpacking
of what can be quite dense
and unintuitive expressions written out
mathematically
in terms of information theories and
expected lagrangians or surprisals
and mutual informations and i say that
for thomas who's been because we've both
been working on trying to get the
simplest uh way of expressing these
important
constraints
intuitively just using equations and
it's not easy
and the reason it's not easy
is that in these information diagrams
when there is no uncertainty
when the uncertainty reaches the entropy
reaches its lower bound the area
disappears at which point for discrete
systems the entropy is zero so when
there's no uncertainty area is equal to
zero h the uncertainty the entropy is
equal to zero
that's how it should be the problem is
when shannon wrote down entropy for
continuous systems that no longer holds
and you get negative areas so there is
no lower bound on the entropy of a
continuous in the continu differential
entropy
um so you really have to go around the
houses
to recover um you know an area that
disappears when in fact it uh it's lower
bounded by minus infinity so that that
particular bit just was for thomas
because i've just emailed him today
about that uh particular
and james saw this problem with
shannon's differential entropy you know
decades and decades ago um
and tried to repair it using something
called continuous entropy and limiting
density of discrete points uh so
all of that worry and all those
conditions just disappear if you just
stick with this these nice information
diagrams where you know that the
if the area isn't there it's shrunk to
zero
awesome
it's like you could be 110 sure
about something
let's go to
figure five
what is happening in figure five
well i think figure five is is showing
more or less what we've seen on the
previous figures but never just
interpreted in the context of in the
context of neuroscience we've got the
same action perception
graphics we were talking about in figure
two or the same equations
um
where the free energy is here being
interpreted in terms of accuracy and
complexity components
and so that that brings us back to what
we talk about in terms of the
interpretation of free energy as a means
of
estimating marginal likelihood or
approximating marginal likelihood and a
bayesian model evidence and the models
should be both as simple as possible
while accurately accounting for some
data
and and i think that's here really to
emphasize that interpretation of
self-evidence and that we've we've
spoken about before the idea that by
minimizing your free and your free
energy you were implicitly maximizing
the evidence for some
internal model
and by putting this explicitly in terms
of the brain
um we're we're now talking about the
kind of model that the brain might
implicitly hold about the outside world
and
the kind of models that might be
required the um
sentient being appearing behavior
and again a nice ring to suggest a
mock-off blanket and
put here explicitly
many questions for another time about
the order of the action perception loop
and
whether
perception precedes action
in principle or in different
computational implementations how
different aspects of the timing of the
execution of different stages
might converge upon similar outcomes and
might not
just noting it
um
in figure 6
we have
sentient behavior and action observation
so what is being shown with a brain and
with these
three graphics beneath
so this is a
nice example of um of what's actually
a slightly older version of active
inference now and is a slightly
different implementation than what we
might use but i think it's a nice
example in that
it highlights the transition from
behavior in terms of continuous
differential equations through to
something that's a bit more sequential
and
behaves in the way that we might
actually think about plans as being one
move and then the next move and then the
thing after that
um and an implicit discretization in
time
and and so that the
the
um the plot shown
in sort of the upper left where we've
got
a series of lines that are kind of
overlapping the red line in bold
and
exactly that one there
is showing what is more or less a sort
of predator-prey-like relationship that
creates these sorts of sequences so if
you can imagine this that that you have
a
alternation between a predator and
some sort of prey
whereas the
prey population increases in size
the predator population will also
increase in size behind that as the
predators have more to feed on
which will in turn cause the prey
population to drop followed again by the
predator population dropping as food
resources become
um more scarce
and and this is known as um as you've
written here winnerless competition or
as a lot of a full terror type dynamic
and the generalization of this you can
have many such sequences where one thing
follows the other and you get this
sequential
set of peaks in what's going on here
now if we would interpret each of those
lines is representing the probability or
the log probability or some some
mapping to the probability of one of
several alternative discrete states
um categorical states so here imagine
we're talking about blue blue green or
red
then we end up generating a sequence of
blues greens reds depending upon the
underlying dynamics so we have a
continuous system that now has the feel
of something sequential
and what's happened here in in
the graphic on top of the brain here
is to associate each of those discrete
categories with different points in
space
so we're now saying that uh if we're if
we're looking at the blue points then
that's going to be associated with this
sort of upper left location in space or
sorry there's a light blue as well bad
choice of color to choose in my part
um
and so each of those sequences is then
associated with a generative model that
says
i expect that when the blue status is
present or the red state is present that
my hand will be drawn towards
one of those states and i predict that
it's as if there is some sort of spring
attached to from my hand to where that
location is
which means that as i as i infer this
sequence i'm sequentially drawn to or i
believe i'm being drawn to each of these
locations in turn
now if i'm predicting if my if my free
energy or my marginal likelihood says
that the most likely states are the ones
that would occur if my arm were really
being drawn in this direction the
actions that then minimize the free
energy are those that fulfill those
predictions so all i have to do is
predict when the kind of proprioceptive
or visual data i might get based on
where my hand is at any one point in in
time
and or predict where the the data that i
would obtain if my hand really were
being drawn in this direction
and the resulting action fulfills
exactly that and creates this sequence
of movements and so what we get out is a
relatively complex motor trajectory that
has an almost autonomous type feel to it
simply by predicting that i'm going to
be drawn to each of these points in
sequence
and this is being used in this
particular
example as a way of simulating
handwriting or something that appears to
be like handwriting simply by moving the
piece of paper underneath
underneath where my hand is moving so
that i end up with this sort of repeated
pattern
and you could imagine that in real
writing that
we may implicitly have a series of
points that we would associate with
different bits of the letters that would
um effectively draw our hand around
those letters as we write them
cool and categorical shifts at the
letter scale at the word scale and so on
could be modeled in a in a hierarchical
way
absolutely and that that sort of
exactly the point in terms of this move
from this um this formulation of active
inference that used to be used now to
explicitly writing down a series of
discrete categorical states and as you
say putting that together in a
hierarchical model
where you can now mix predictions of a
discrete categorical sort with short
trajectories in a continuous
state and a continuous state space
awesome we'll complete our lightning
tour of the last three figures
so
here's figure seven
just
um for for reference we looked at figure
three
we saw some faces and names and now
we're seeing figure seven
what is being shown here
so here i think we're dealing with what
what is a limitation of what we saw on
the previous slide
so when we were thinking about these
fairly complex trajectories that had an
almost autonomous feel like to them
um it's still only a relatively simple
sort of behavior
implicitly it's just dealing with the
replication of some potentially quite
complex or even arbitrary pattern
um but to become really autonomous to to
behave in an intelligent like way
really what we need is to be able to
select between alternative sequences and
alternative patterns
and what this slide is showing us is
this idea this one way or
the way that we appear to evaluate
different
trajectories or the probability of of
pursuing those trajectories
is in terms of this expected free energy
function which can be decomposed in a
similar way to to what we expect of the
free energy function so because in blue
the free energy functional being
decomposed into our complexity and
accuracy terms and various other
decompositions
but in the in the upper panel um we're
now looking at the decomposition of the
expected free energy
into into analogous type terms and we've
spoken about some of those already so
here the intrinsic value is equivalent
to the information gain we were speaking
about before
whereas the extrinsic value is more like
our
expected utility or
the the degree to which we prefer a
particular outcome
um and just as on the previous slide
each of the faces relates to different
ways that that can be interpreted under
specific circumstances where then
where particular parts of
that expression are irrelevant um or
don't master so in the absence of
ambiguity we end up with behaviors that
are entirely risk driven
and so we might get back to things like
kale control type formulations
any notes or we'll go to eight
okay
here we are in eight
i thought for a second that we've seen
this before but um it's a subtly
different reworking of one of the
previous figures isn't it with them
here's five with the expected free
energy yeah correct f in five and then
just an a path and now we have
um in eight
g in the top
i suppose this is the move that we were
talking about before in terms of when
the active states are effectively hidden
from the internal states and becomes
something that are themselves inferred
um
so you can see here the the absence of
any arrow connecting a to the
variational free energy box
which is implicitly saying that the
action itself is something that we have
to draw inferences about
and here the expected free energy is the
way in which we can do that
it's inference on action about action
about the causes of action
just many ways that have been
highlighted for how
inference and action are weaving
together
and different
model architectures that might be
more didactic
more illustrative
more pragmatic for a given context or a
given type of thing that has a certain
sparsity to its coupling
and to
close on figure 9 and then we can have
last thoughts what is shown in figure 9
so figure 9 is a nice example of the
application of this information seeking
aspect of the expected free energy
and to a task in which um that there is
uncertainty about the orientation of the
face that's presented to the active
infant scheme
and
the alternative trajectories the
alternative parts of autonomous states
that can be selected here are the
alternative
eye movements or circads that can be
performed
and so choosing the
or
evaluating the probability of each
account depends upon evaluating the
potential information gain associated
with those
which is effectively the information
gain i get in terms of the eventual
orientation of the face
um i think in practice this
if i remember rightly that this um
formulation focused very much on the
ambiguity term
um
and um i think a subsequently being
updated in various ways but again it
kind of focused on the the continuous
schemes and
um and provides a nice early example of
how um information gains worked into the
active inference type formulas we tend
to use practically
awesome in our final few minutes
we we look at the questions that we've
looked at the end of every live stream
and
it would be awesome to hear
where things go from here from this
recent
preprint from the textbook
what are some of the areas that any of
you are
interested in or that are now possible
to head in
i'll go first then i don't have to go
last again
difficult question to answer um
there are so many ways you can take this
i i think it's gone beyond the capacity
of any single group or person to to
really pursue all the all the directions
so nearly every field that we've
mentioned um you know is probably the
focus of at least one if not you know
several groups um around the world small
embryonic groups but certainly working
earnestly on uh the different levels of
of application um technically what what
thomas and i um no that's not quite true
one thing that thomas and i have been
doing
is um trying to write the next simpler
paper um so the your the the free energy
principle made simpler
already
wasn't that simple in the end so the
idea is now to
work towards a four-page paper that has
everything you need to know to
understand the free energy principle
the most recent ones down to abouts of
eight pages
and what it does is it just drills down
on the path integral formulation
and in particular
the simplifications afforded by not
worrying about non-equilibrium
steady-state densities and just looking
at the densities over paths and just
taking away all the unnecessary
equations and this drilling down on what
matters
and to me what really matters is in the
last
sentence here and implicit in the last
figure that you were discussing
which is curiosity
which i think is the key thing that
distinguishes current ai from agi and
you know true intelligence and
understanding um resolving uncertainty
about your sense-making understanding of
a world and understanding the
mathematical imperatives that describe
that kind of behavior so this is i'll
end where i started which is all about
curiosity
excellent thank you
thomas
as god says it is a really difficult
series of questions to answer and
they're i think there are always more
interesting directions to go in than
there is time to pursue them which is
why
again as carl says it's important that
there are so many groups out there who
are taking an interest and focusing in
on these issues
um
certainly the idea of making things
simpler i think is an important
direction to going
um i think it's also
for me one of the interesting things is
um it is also thinking about application
in
the setting of
disease processes and trying to
understand how um
how different disease processes can be
framed in terms of alternative priors
and just as a way of
i hope at some point providing useful
clinical characterizations of different
um kinds of pathology different kinds of
trajectories and different kinds of
steady states um
and
understanding how different therapeutic
options might change the path through
some um some space of
prior beliefs at various different
temporal and spatial scales as we've
spoken about
and so for me i think that that's one of
the areas i'm particularly interested in
seeing how things develop
thank you blue
as i was saying the other day i'm really
starting to
think of active inference the way that
like in every
in every situation and in every
circumstance that i find myself in
i find myself wondering
how can i formulate this in an active
inference model and i did the same thing
when i was in art school and learning
how to draw in a very realistic way i
was learning to draw people and objects
in the way that i saw them
and now i'm i'm looking at situations
that i find myself in and um you know
where before i would be in conversation
with someone looking at their earlobe
like wondering how can i best like
represent that on a piece of paper um
now i find myself in situations like
wondering how would this fit into the
active inference framework so i think
that there are many um
that the horizon is very broad and there
are many avenues where we can
tread
the art and science of curiosity
so it's an excellent conclusion
carl and thomas thank you for joining
these discussions
and
everyone who
is listening
thank you and we hope to see you in
actin flab or in any other
fractal aspect of what we're all doing
so thanks again everybody thanks blue
and
see you in the next discussion
bye
you